A Guide to the Additional Papers of John Lloyd Newcomb, 1875-1947 (bulk 1899-1947)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of John Lloyd Newcomb 1875-1947 (bulk 1899-1947)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.071
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was formerly MSS 2755 and was transferred to the University of Virginia Archives on August 11, 2006 and reprocessed.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Lloyd Newcomb was born in Gloucester County, Virginia, in 1881, and died in 1954. Newcomb attended graduate school in the University of Virginia Department of Civil Engineering, was appointed an adjunct Professor of Civil Engineering in 1905 by the Board of Visitors (1905-1925), and also served as Dean of Engineering (1925-1931). Newcomb served as Assistant to the President (1926-1931) under Edwin A. Alderman, spent two years as Acting President upon Alderman's death (1931-1933), and succeeded Alderman as the University of Virginia's second president in 1933 until his retirement in 1947.
Newcomb saw the University through the Depression and the Second World War and managed its physical expansion, including the construction of Scott Stadium, the Bayly Art Museum, and Alderman Library. After his death, Newcomb was revealed to be a member of the Seven Society, the University of Virginia secret society known for its gifts to and in support of the University community. In 1958 the Seven Society donated $17,777.77 to establish a loan fund for faculty and students in Newcomb's honor.
An engineering professorship, the John Lloyd Newcomb Professor of Material Science and Engineering Physics, is endowed in Newcomb's memory, and the student union building at Virginia, Newcomb Hall, is named after him.
Scope and Content
These papers are chiefly the personal papers of University of Virginia President John Lloyd Newcomb and his wife, Grace, ca. 1875, 1896-1947, ca. 1,275 items (7 boxes, ca. 2.5 linear feet) including some course notebooks and papers, from his days as an engineering graduate student, with some material associated with his role as president. The files pertaining to his service as University President include: the budget; construction on the Chemical Building (1941); correspondence with miscellaneous state and federal government officials about possible programs and involvement with the University; courses taught at the University; photographs and prints; press notices and songs about the University; reports including specifications for the new library building (Alderman) and others by Rowland Egger, H.D. Albright, and Wilson Gee.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically by the title and in reverse chronological order within each folder, except for the two boxes of book donation receipts placed at the end of the collection due to their size.
Contents List
- Blueprint of the Almirall System of Forced Hot Water Heating, Dawson's Row, Parsonage, Monroe Hill, and Student's Rooms on Professor Snavley's Residence; Block Plan University of Virginia Showing Proposed Layout of Mains and Buildings to be heated by Central Hot Water Heating; and Heating of Cottage Adjacent to Parsonage by forced hot water, 1920-1925 (Oversize 1)
- Budget Book [of the Newcomb Family], 1931-1945 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Budget- University, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Construction- Chemical Building, 1941 February (Box-folder 1:3)
- Correspondences- Cards, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Correspondences- Government, 1915-1946 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondences- Mrs. Newcomb- Women's Field Army, American Society for the Control of Cancer, 1931-1945, Chiefly printed. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Correspondences- Mrs. Newcomb- Floral Cards, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Correspondences- Mrs. Newcomb- Get Well Cards and Letters, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Correspondences- University- Department of Civil Engineering, 1925 (Box-folder 1:9)
  Includes correspondence about the blueprints and heating of the Parsonage on Professor Snavley's Residence on Dawson's Row.
- Courses- Applied Mathematics in Surveying and Leveling, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Courses- Bridge Construction- General, 1912-1918 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Courses- Bridge Construction- Notebooks, 1896-[1897] (Box-folder 2:2)
- Courses- Civil Engineering- General, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Courses- Civil Engineering- Course Book, n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
- Courses- History, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Courses- Masonry Construction- General, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Courses- Masonry Construction- Notebooks, 1899-[1945] (Box-folder 3:1)
- Courses- Municipal Engineering, 1899 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Courses- Physics, 1900-1902 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Courses- Railway Engineering- General, 1905-1908 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Courses- Railway Engineering- Notebooks, [1905-1908] (Box-folder 3:5)
- Courses- Road Engineering, 1906-1924 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Courses- Roof Construction, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Courses- Surveying and Leveling- General, 1901-1930 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Courses- Surveying and Leveling- Field Book, n.d. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Courses- Surveying and Leveling- Notebooks, 1901-1902 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Courses- Surveying and Leveling- Notebooks, 1903-1904, n.d. (Box-folder 4:2)
- Courses- Surveying and Leveling- Notebooks, n.d. (Box-folder 4:3)
- Courses- Waterworks and Sewers, 1905 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Fraternities, 1904-1933 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Miscellaneous, ca. 1925-1945 (Box-folder 4:6)
  Includes a Deed of Trust, Bookmark, and War Ration Book.
- Patrons of Husbandry Certificate, Otter Ridge, Campbell County, Virginia, 1875 May 10 (Oversize 4)
- Photographs- Mechanical Laboratory, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 4:7)
- Photographs- People including Edwin A. Alderman, statue of Thomas Jefferson, statue of [Voltaire?], group shots with John Lloyd Newcomb, 1931-1944, n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)
- Photographs and Prints- University of Virginia, including the Lawn, aerial shots, mechanical laboratory, Cabell Hall, pavilions, and Rotunda, 1913-[1945] (Box-folder 4:9)
- Press Notices and Songs about the University, 1935-1946 (Box-folder 4:10)
- Report- Architectural Specifications for new library building and general, n.d. (Box-folder 4:11)
- Report- Conference on Administrative Reorganization of Government held at the School of Political Science, 1937 June-November (Box-folder 4:12)
- Report- Construction of Indianapolis Motor Speedway, n.d. (Box-folder 4:13)
- Small Cards, n.d. (Box-folder 4:14)
- Report- Isham Randolph and Company, 1918 (Box-folder 5:1)
- Report- National Universities, [1932-1945] (Box-folder 5:2)
- Report- The Organization of Peace on the Administrative Level by Rowland Egger, 1945 October-November (Box-folder 5:3)
- Report- School and Community Drama in Virginia by H.D. Albright, 1942 (Box-folder 5:4)
- Report- Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation and Speech by Charles A. Beard, [1931-1945] (Box-folder 5:5)
- Social Science Research Organization in American Universities and Colleges by Wilson Gee, ca. 1934, Typescript. (Box-folder 5:6)
- Tourism Brochures, 1934, n.d. (Box-folder 5:7)
- University Correspondence, 1919-1942 (Box-folder 5:8)
- University Report- Committee on School of Nursing, 1946 May 23 (Box-folder 5:9)
- University Report- Tentative Classification of Positions, 1937 March 31 (Box-folder 5:10)
- Book Donation Receipts of Newcomb (A-M), [1902-1947] (Box 6)
- Book Donation Receipts of Newcomb (M-Z), [1906-1947] (Box 7)